right hello and welcome this is active
inference live stream
63.1 it's November 7th
2023 we're here with mikal pikarski and
we'll be hearing a presentation followed
by a discussion on incorporating
variational free energy models into
mechanisms the case of predictive
processing under the free energy
principle so looking forward to this
lecture and discussion thank you for
joining and off to
you thank you very much Daniel thank you
for invitation uh this is a great honor
for me and very
nice uh I'm little stressed I hope uh my
presentation will be
uh interesting for you and um give a
chance to take a new some new ideas
concerning the the basian models
especially productive processing under
the free energy principle so uh my talk
is based uh on my recent papers which I
published after after many many months
of revisions in centes and I
will sketch The View which I try to
develop here uh which I think has some
interesting
implication also for the discussion in
the field of bayian modeling like in The
Wider context of philosophy of
Neuroscience of philosophy of uh
cognitive science so I will try to
justify the three
hypothesis uh one General and two more
specific concerning uh the predict
processing and free energy principle so
the first one idea which
I found in recent paper of some
philosophers of mechanistic explanations
is the is the idea that
um there
phenomena I think that there are
neurocognitive phenomena which uh should
be
explained not only in the terms of the
composing the mechanism which uh is
related to this phenomena but also
should incorporate the the constraints
from the environmental constraints and
the flows of free energy I will uh
be I will defend the view according to
which if you want to explain those
mechanism those phenomena we have to
take an account of flows of free energy
and the notion of free energy of course
in the work of those mechanists uh is
related to the thermodynamic free energy
but I will try to show that um the free
energy we can understand also in the
terms of interenational or variational
free energy this is the first hypothesis
the second uh hypothesis is um this is
not my idea because we found in many
papers of Jacob ho or pavesi the idea
that predictive processing provides a
sketch of mechanism in other words
predictive processing is computational
framework which has mechanistic or or in
which can offer a mechanistic
explanation of its Target
phenomena and I will try to to connect
the two my
hypothesis and shows that but
mechanistic predictive processing takes
a informational constraints from the
free energy principle in other words we
can uh in uh
integrate free energy Principle as
normative Theory normative principle
with process Theory predictive
processing using the
mechanistic uh picture mechanistic idea
of explanations so let's start from the
first uh hypothesis
um I think that there is a general and
common agree in the field in the works
of some authors from cognitive uh
science from philosophy of
Neuroscience uh the view
which
schematically called new mechanical
philosophy According to which the
explanation of phenomena is a matter of
the composing this phenomena in to
underlying mechanism so when we want to
explain phenomena for example this is a
view who defend the the car Craver or
William
Beal and the others when we want to
explain phenomena not only cognitive but
also biological social canena we have to
decompose the mechanism which is
responsible for the realization of this
phenomenon and this mechanism can be
traed as a
uh mechanism which casual product the
phenomena or a mechanism which is
responsible in the terms of cons
dtive responsibility for the realization
of the phenomena and uh those authors
who and those Traditions which craer in
his book explaining the brain calls the
system Traditions claims that
explanation is a matter of finding the
systems the mechanism which should be
described should be should be identified
by scientists and should be decomposed
into into Parts into components should
we should recognize the relation between
those components and the we should
recognize and describe the
organization which rules of the
relations between the components and it
means that uh we can think about the
mechanism in terms of hierarchical
organization because if we look come
this figure from The Book of the Craver
phenomena phenomena are based
hierarchically on the
underlying uh structure of hierarchical
structure of U mechanism the low and
higher level mechanism and according to
our uh scientific aims according to uh
our strategy we can uh looking for the
more deeper
or more deeper mechanism concerning for
example
how the level of a biological
organization to the level of the
physiological organization and so on and
one of
the most important authors in the field
of mechanistic explanation the field of
uh new mechanism William Beal um in
recent latest
paper uh he little Chang the standard
view on the composition he claims that
characteristic of the composition or
normative strategy of the composition
mechanical explanation should
be reing we should reink this strategy
why because there are high level
cognitive
mechanisms which cannot be described
Solly in the terms of hierarchical
organization or in the terms of
casual uh relations because there are
some kind of mechanism which are as uh
and Collex claims which are active
control mechanism they are mechanism
which are responsible for production the
phenomena what kind of phenomena the
active phenomena active active
structures like uh bily movements
responsible for body movement and
physiological process and CRA Bal cran
sorry that those
mechanism of course they play a central
uh ual role in the hierarchical
organization but they also a components
of complex network of heterarchical web
of control systems and they play its
casual
role they casual Ro because they perform
a given function in this heterarchical
web why it is possible because in this
sense those pH those phenomena are the
uh are mutually constrainted by the
other elements we can call their
constraints and they are uh and they are
active or they derive their casual
efficieny because they are constraint
systems and um in in opinion of Beal uh
and the other authors who co-work with
him it is important to
reink uh our old uh image of of DEC
composition
because in standard view on the
decomposition we don't take an account
uh on two elements on uh
constraints which make
given
mechanism uh active in the sense of the
being part of heterarchical web and the
second point is the energy because
biological and mechanisms cognitive
mechanism are always um related to the
flows of the free energy which they uh
transform which they uh Pro
process and why this is important
because according to beel he claims what
is characteristic for biological
mechanism uh in the context in the
contrast to the other mechanis is that
the biological mechanism are dissipative
structures it means that they Ur and
maintained in the context in the fridge
in fridge free energy is being
dissipated
and if we don't uh don't
incorporate this element of transforming
of um processing the flows of free
energy we in the facto we don't really
explain why given mechanis or given
systems have behaviors as back and B
claims completely unconstrained system
will have no
behaviors and I will f think
that
uh if you want to explain neurocognitive
mechanism we have to adopt the view
which I describ in my paper as a the
constraint based mechanism approach and
according to VI it's heris mechanistic
explanation of at least some cognitive
phenomena should be based or should
incorporate dimensions of constraints
element of the environment which
makes mechanism active and the flows of
free
energy and this is the first piece of uh
my idea and uh second is that I think
that we can try to uh demonstrate this
idea
in
uh
one example from
cognitive contemporary cognitive science
and I will try to adopt this idea into
the frame of predictive processing
so now I'll will sketch a a short view
about predictive processing framework
and why this is important for me uh to
try to test this this framework into the
context of the constraint based
mechanism approach um so predictive
coders uh develop the C and the helan
idea that that our cognitive systems our
brains don't have a direct access to the
causes of information we received by the
input and the uh and they claim that uh
the central the main function of the
brain on the central nervous system is
to minimize uh uncertainity which is
described in the terms of minimizing
long-term minimization of average
prediction
error uh how it is possible how brain
can do this uh it possible because the
brain inhabit or embedded the virtual
informational structure with which
predictive C byan describe as generative
model and the generative model is
hierarchical and
multilevel structures which transform
pro pro process the information coming
from the IND why because in this way the
brain can minimize the So-Cal prediction
ER or the crepancies the differences
between the state of the model state of
the organism and the information coming
from the from the environment because
successful minimalization of prediction
error has many
adaptive uh benefits so uh this is
General um picture uh now we should look
more uh closer to this image and try to
develop a
um formal technical language
so uh we can use this the idea which
develops a take to think about the
relation between the events in the word
in the time term
of relation between cause and effect but
what we receive is the observation we
receive by the sensory input
observations and if the idea developed
by predictive coders coming from
homehold is that we don't have an access
to the straight through States as
understood as the causes of the
observation so we have to infert the
true
states to act successfully in the
environment and how it is possible to
infer to guess the true States
responsible for the observation we
receive so there is a development of the
hel idea of unconscious inference and
ban claims that this idea can be
translate into the thinking about the
statistical inference what kind of
statistical inference as we know this is
the bayian bayian inference but what
does it mean the generative model
minimize prediction error or infer the
true
States um using the ban inference
talking
inference um Rises um
a small problem because B inference
exact B inference is in inra hard uh we
cannot compute exact ban inference and
the idea which develop for example
Carone is
that our models our brains using models
generative
model don't compute exact Bion inference
but it uses the simpler version of ban
inference they
approximate they uses approximation of
ban inference so in other words if the
story is uh correct then um continuous
minimalization of prediction
error can be described or understood or
explained in the terms of approximation
of ban inference and this is this
approximation is possible because model
minimizing prediction error
simultaneously
minimize a certain
quantity which frone calls varation
energy the quantity
which is always greater than or equal to
suor and using this
quantity uh model iteratively
update the internal parameters upd the
internal States
and uh in this in that way can infer the
most probable to uh states which is
responsible for the observation which
model refers so uh and according to
predictive processing uh as I read it
correctly what is characteristic for the
brain is it that the
brain main function is to uh processing
information in the terms of ban
approximation and I try to unpack this
idea uh and uh read this and try to read
this in the context of new mechanical
philosophy so this is the first step the
second one is to justify that predictive
processing can be connected with
mechanical philosophy and um in many
papers of
weski hares Shava ho we we see good
arguments uh According to which
predictive processing as computational
architecture provides the scientist
so-called sketch uh of mechanisms what
is sketch of mechanism this is the idea
developed by Pini and Kaplan and they
that sketch of the mechanism is the
incomplete representation of mechanism
it means this is there some kind of
representation of mechanism when the
scientist omitted some components some
parts of the mechanism and good SK
sketch of the mechanism should lead us
to the schema of mechanism which is the
complete
representation of constitutive element
of given mechanism so if predictive
processing give give us a chance to to
to to write a sketch of the
mechanism uh and and if predictive
processing is about the neural function
of the brain then um if the
view which I developed uh after the
ideas of Beal and Collex if this if this
view of the constraint based mechanism
purose approach uh is correct then I
will claim that if predictive processing
if predictive ERS want to build a
mechanistic explanation of cognitive
phenomena they should include into the
explanation flows of free energy because
without this uh flows without the
constraint of informational or in
general in is free energy uh we don't
cannot explain how it is possible that
mechanism operates and is active as long
as this energy is
available and it does is which I defend
in this paper in sentence is that
predictive processing
models should uh include informational
constraints if they are to be
mechanistic of course if we think about
predict processing as the way to explain
the function of the
brain and of course there is one natural
questions because many authors will
claim that the good uh theoretical
normative uh principle for building
models in predictive processing offer
the free energy principle so the the
question arise does uh the free energy
principle can offer this constraints for
predictive architect and I will be claim
that yet yes the FB offers these
constraints
but of course we should try
to justify this this St more uh
specifically so uh
but we've got we find
an the one big uh problem when we talk
when we look into
the uh 2018 paper of William Beal when
he introduced the
idea of uh necessity of uh including the
free energy flows into explanations he
directly write that the notion of free
energy uh which he developed in his
papers in his view is distinct from the
free
energy uh principle or free energy
articulated by Carone and the others in
other words he say that okay we should
include into explanations flows of the
free energy but this is the
thermodynamic free energy we cannot use
the other kind of the energy because uh
because this is distinct
Notions uh in the same year in 2018 uh
friston published a draft a print of his
book of free energy principle for a
particular physic and he said something
what contradict with the view of the B
he said that her
istically free energy in the ter
thermodynamical free energy is
consistent with the variational free
energy means that pron
claims uh something qu contradict the
tesis of the back and I think that it is
possible to justify the thesis of fron
but possibly I try to do this in
different way
than then FR then Frist do this does
this so
um for me as a person without good
formal uh preparation to reading the
paper of ciston U it was hard
to find a good way reading of his paper
on his Cooperators so um but I think
that we can try to reconstruct the
idea uh which supporters of the free
energy principle um develop and this
ideas can be commonly described as
something what I call the ban mechanics
argument uh the first site I wrote here
is coming from the paper of Max ramstead
and he claims that at of biasan
mechanics is the variational free energy
principle so the Freestone in his latest
paper proposed the idea of the loping of
the bian mechanics the bian mechanics uh
which uh can investigate describe and
offer the thetical background for an
explanation what is fre principle what
is foral free energy and
um why this idea is it's important for
me
because um first will
claim that every kind of mechanism each
mechanism can be
treated as an expression of some kind of
mechan mechanics we've got classical
mechanics we got quantum mechanics uh
thermodynamic statistical also bial
mechanics and every kind of mechanics
has it own rified constructs those
constructs can be understood as
thermodynamic energy temperature or
variational free
energy and uh what is important is that
that those constructs those ried
constructs those Notions are Justified
and can be used only in the realm of
given type of mechanics it means that it
is possible that we've got some rified
constructs which we can use on the based
in the realm of the one kind of the
mechanics but we cannot use this in the
other type of Mechanics for example when
we talk about the den notion of the
uh temperature it can be it will be used
in different way in the realm of quantum
and in the realm of statistical
mechanics and it means that if we take
the construct like variational free
energy on thermodynamic free free energy
from the point of the view of this
argument it means that all of these
constructs are relative or
related to the description and method of
measurement we it which we use in the uh
specific type of
mechanics and what does it mean it means
that there is no
um ontological uh we don't have a good
ontological argument to claim something
like that that for example statistical
mechanics is more primary than for
example classic or bi mechanic why
because every kind of mechanism each
type of mechanics can be trated as a
complementary description of the
behavior of a dynamic systems and it
means that the
most uh primary the most basic structure
we try to explain describe in terms of
mechanics
dynamical uh systems or the Dial Systems
so when according to fre it means that
ban mechanics can be treated as all
others kind of mechanics which we find
in physics but what is specifical for
this mechanic as I said is the
Assumption of variational energy which
is strictly related to the Assumption of
mar of
blankets pron will uh claim that this
additional constraints the constraints
of Mark of blankets makes possible to
speak of states of something as relative
as something different of something else
uh and why this is important to make a
possibility to think to talk about for
example internal and external States
because um
this talking this the possibility of
talking about the different states uh
directly applicable and directly
important to the living organism and for
example neural structures
friston in his book claim
that uh every type of
mechanics ignore Assumption of a mark
blanket and the Assumption of ration
energy and um and in some implicit sense
will claim that the state outside
blanket and the states out of blanket
this difference between those kind of
States can be ignored for why
because if this um why I thinking is
correct every kind of mechanics give us
a chance give us a possibility to talk
about the systems we try to describe in
terms of heatbed or thermal reserver it
means that every kind of mechanics
except quantum
mechanics uh give us a possibility to
talk about the states as in equilibrium
steady state
so uh
and according to this argument we should
say that variational free energy can be
applied and Justified only in the real
of basian mechanics and this application
help us to describe explain why some
things are autonomous or active why some
things can be as as Bal s dissipative
structures but it means that vational
free energy give us a chance to describe
some kind of phenomena some kind of
system as autonomous or active but and
simultaneously ter dynamical free energy
can be implied in the realm of the the
object which we can try uh which we want
to explain in the terms of statistics or
statist as a statistical
emble
um and this is uh this is why FR will
claim that both ational free energy and
thermodynamical free energy are
consistent because they are two
consequences or expression we can say
the same more Elemental think the think
which can more Elemental more basic
mechanistic or maybe Quantum nature and
it means that thermodynamical free
energy and variational free energy are
the notion or constructs um which we can
trade as the as a two side of the one
coin and uh
um uh it's and using them is dependent
of our method of measurements of our
scientific interest from the
our strategy to investigate in phenomena
but they are complementary in the sense
that they offer uh the scientist that um
the possibility of describe dynamical
systems from the two other sides but
this those sides are
complementary uh and how we should under
understand and interpretate the the
bayian mechanics
argument because I think this argument
should be interpretate in more
philosophical more specific way
if the thermodynamical free energy and
vational free energy are two sides or
are related to as two aspect of more
Primal Dynamics uh there is still open
the questions what about what we talk
when we talk about systems which
minimize varation of energy and when we
talk about the direction the the flows
of the thermodynamical free energy and I
think that um this ultra realistic or
super realistic interpretation literal
interpretation of this argument is not
correct because
it seems that we should
interpretate a construct like like
thermodynamical andir energy as uh the
useful useful function which are which
uses which uh justification are related
to
our scientific models and so on um in
other ways there will be the problem to
defend the tesis of FreeOnes that the
pan and stasic mechanics are equivalent
formulation of the same thing I think
the the same thing about which with
friston talk is the dynamical systems
and we try to find a good tools to
describe the systems but it means that
we don't have a good tools which
represent or map the uh real structure
of the
systems and it means that the notion we
use like verion energ and thermodynamic
of energy should be understood as the
con constructs which are related and and
ultimately reduced to the method uh of
measurement descriptions the method we
use so uh it means that when we talk
about the consistency or complementarity
of vational fre energy in
thermodynamical free energy we don't
have any we don't make any ontological
com commitments any monological
assumption about the representational
architecture propers of the target
systems it means that the models are
which are based on the free energy
principle address the Casual structure
of the word in the sense that they are
epistemically useful we can use them in
the practice of model building but they
are not epistemically useful in the
sense that we describe the real
properties which we can literally
describe as uh generative models as
varation energy and so on and so
on and uh I think uh when we talk about
the free energy principle the
instrumental and realistic
interpretation is correct and the free
energy principle doesn't imply any
ontological solution about the target
phenomena but um from the point of the
view of my my argument there is one
problem because this instrument Al
interpretation of Frisian
argument doesn't have any
mechanistical specific
mechanistic implication we don't
anything talk about mechanistic
character of the
phenomena uh why this is important
because when we come back to the field
of uh philosophia of new mechanical the
field of new mechanical philosophy we
all see that I think there is in very
General there's a common view that we
should think uh about mechanism in a
realistic manner what does it mean the
the view which I try to describe here is
soal mechanistic
realism According to
which uh we should think about
the stru the structures the the the
entities in the world as the structure
which are in some sense sense
richer than M aggregation of causes why
this is important
because me mechanism which we try to
identify the compos should
be should be produced by some kind of
structures and the structures should be
more richer than a simple aggregation of
the causes and this is the four part
first part of this argument and the
second con connected to the idea I try
to develop is that that there are some
of those
structures whose at first organization
cannot be reduced to an aggregation of
the causes of causes and
second uh this organization should be
explained in terms of mechanism which
are
constrained by a flows of information
flows of thermodynamic energy and
described maybe in terms of minimizing
rational Fergy in other words I will be
claimed that if we adopt the mechanistic
realism we
should try to say that there are such
phenomena such structures the
explanation of which should take into
account the energetic
constraint which we can try to describe
in terms of vational free
energy and this in this and um if we try
to adopt the the the image of coming
from the mechanistic realism we will
defend the view which I
describe as moderate realism about by
modeling or moderate realism about
processing ande principle in this
moderate realistic
interpretations we can s say that system
minimizes prediction error or minimizes
variational free energy because it
implements in some way some casual
mechanism that can be described
approximately in terms of minimizing VAR
energy are simultaneously maximizing
Mutual information between internal
States and sensory
States and it means there uh we can
identify describe and the compose some
kind of mechanism which we should trade
as system of mutual constraints that
restrict the flow of information the
flows also the
thermodynamic uh free energy to perform
work in such a way that those mechanism
minimize or should minimize discrepancy
between internal State between the
parameter of the model between the
prediction of the model and uh the
information coming from the environment
in which given systems uh act and live
why because
without this
um without taking those constraints
flows of information we cannot describe
and explain why those kind of mechanism
or why the kind what uh this kind of
organism are at non equilibrium steady
States so um and I think that we can
find in in the field of thermodynamics
of information and also with the the
work of craft freem argument which I
called argument from neur
computation uh good argument for the
moderate realistic interpretation ofp
and freeer principle and according to
this
argument we can say that there is always
tradeoff between neural information
processing and Thermon thermodynamic
energy poost it means that every time
when biological sensor detect a
changeing the environment every time
when biological organ process the
informations this uh processing
information or detection a change in
environment is proportional to the
amount of information is proportional to
the um
some minimum uh energy in term of
thermodynamics so every time when uh
system transer process information every
time uh there is ex minimum cost of a
thermodynamic energy and this argument
from Nur computation could be this
related to
the uh formal investigation from coming
from the FR monograph about thein
equality piece of this book about the
yin equality is really hard
um but uh one and a half years ago I I
was
talking with car friston about this
argument about the yin equality and I
think we can try to reformulate in more
nonformal way and according to the Ain
equality if we interpretate this in the
realm of the free energy
principle this equality allows us to
connect variational free energy with
thermodynamical free energy in this
sense that the when we want to describe
and moving one system from one state to
another and this moving in the system we
can as uh uh creating dying the
information there is a certain amount of
thermodynamic uh work cost and
thermodynamic and action which should be
entailed by this moving uh in other
words when we look into
the a generative model in our brains we
will say that every time when the model
update
belief in in the sense that every time
when model change information uh in the
internal state of the model every time
there is an thermodynamical work cost so
the belief updating in the ban
generative model is strictly related the
thermodynamic cost of this belief
updating and I think
that uh moderate realistic
interpretation should explain us how
it's possible
because because uh when we talk about
the belief upd generative model when we
talk about the minimalization of error
literally we we literally we don't map
the formal structures we use onto the
target
phenomena h i don't claim that there are
real generative model in our brains I
don't talk that our brains
uh optimize base and so on but I will
claim that there are some structures in
our head there are some structures in
the W that are richer than simple
aggregation of cod
and those structures Implement some
casual mechanism that scientist can
approximately describes in terms of
models which minimize perational uh
energy or prediction
error as and I agree with u the thesis
of kof and colleagues that uh our models
fit the data without literal make M
mapping yes our model is are true
because they are approximation of the
data and I think that uh we can think
about the predictive processing
model incorporated or related uh or
integrated sorry with uh the free energy
Principle as some kind of
approximation of the data which we want
to investigate a specific type of the
data uh uh
like our neural organs and so on and I
think that we should distinguish and
remember about three distinct elements
the fact the free energy Principle as
formal principle the formal principle
which doesn't assume any ontological uh
assumption and doesn't imply any
ontological commitments about the target
phenoma the predictive processing
framework as mechanistic comput
models which are grounded from the one
side in this formal principle which uh
the form when the for principle offers
the uh variational methods variational
uh Notions and from the other side on
theistic of mechanistic explanations and
the thir the biological systems the
target systems that predictive
processing and bi Asians employed to
model which are based
uh which are uh independent of the
implication or on the language of the
three energ principle and also uh which
are independent from the language and uh
ontological implication of uh process
Theory like predictive processing
so uh and in going to conclusion so um I
will claim that the reference to the
informational constraints
allows the scien scientist to explain
the neural organs the brains not only as
a kind of physical material physical
mechanism but also as a systems which
have homeostatic Futures homeostatic
nature so and I will be claims that it
means that a full satisfaction
explanation of how the brain works not
only how the brain uh can be treated in
terms of statistical or
uh classical mechanics but also with the
terms of uh thinking about the the brain
as active as and the part of living
body uh a full explanation of uh brain
as part of the living body uh requires
taking into account informational cont
constraints which I believe can be
characterized and described in terms of
ban operational free energy
minimalization
and the last uh one
conclusion uh is the observation that
from the point of the view of the
argument I try to develop is that the
free energy principle is also normative
in the sense that it sets a norm that
should be met by mechanistically
non-trivial process Theory or predictive
processing models assuming the
correctness of the constraint based
mechanism approach okay thank you very
much that that's all what I
have thank
you great
presentation I'll make a first comment
meanwhile anyone who's watching live is
welcome to ask a
question okay
well I would like to applaud this great
talk you connected the scholarship and
the framings that are used in the
philosophy of mechanistic
accounts with free energy principle
active inference predictive
processing and I think you articulated
several lines of arguments that were in
the
literature including where there was
change or even partial um incoherence or
just partial
ambiguity certainly
ambiguity related
to
um justifications or understandings of
the relationship
between thermodynamic free energy and
mechanics and basian free energy and
mechanics and that is a very wide space
with everyone saying things like it's a
purely formal
resemblance and it's just a convenient
computational her istic used in science
and physics and engineering and there's
just no need to worry about more than
that ranging
to arguments that that they are co-
extent or that they have different kinds
of statuses so I very much appreciate in
your paper and in this
presentation that according to the way
that different discussions about
mechanism have been carried out in the
biological
sciences using that setup to clarify
some of these discussions in
this
field that are all great to approach
with kind of a first principal View and
it's helpful to see how it connects with
the arguments of like Craver and
Beckel he thanks um I agreed that I try
to develop some arguments which are uh
which exist in the
current literature but um for example
when I read uh the paper of beel I think
that the this
idea doesn't be directly explicitly
um
articulated and um I think that
Beal should be doesn't agree with my
argument my interpretation of his view
because because of the variational uh
free energy but I still believe this is
very very basic
intuition uh but this intuition is said
that if we if we think about the part of
the human organism if we think about the
brains what is more specific for the
brains is that the brain process
information not brain brain process the
thermodynamic energy no brain
uh process or produce some kind of
hormones but the brain process the
information and this information is very
important for uh for a living organism
and I think that this intuition could
should be
tasted uh in the in the field of uh on
in the field of science or maybe in the
field of philosophy of
Neuroscience and
uh I'm not so sure that can this is
possible to to taste it but uh I think
that this is important to description or
explanation of those mechanism that
those mechanism as the are the mechanism
of transform processing
information and
possibly uh possibly maybe it's enough
to say that okay those mechanism
information with the which the brain
process it's not important to
explanation of how it is is
possible but um I think that predictive
CS the the supporters of the free energ
principes s something important and they
claims that what is specific for the
brain is not only that the process
information but also is is the process
in some specific way uh
using something what we can describe in
terms of ban programation or more wider
as a statistical inference and I think
that and I think
if predictive coders predictive
processing uh is a fruitful strategy of
explanation in the field of
Neuroscience ER if the model builds by
predictive coders are uh scientifically
useful then uh we should take an uh we
should use theistic coming from the free
energy
principle that um
take it seriously okay because I don't
want
to I try to say
that uh talking about the brains which
use which uses which use the generative
model which approximates by as inference
this is not the way of talking way of
speaking I think that we don't only
describe but uh but this the word we use
the notion we use as I said are in some
way correct response to the some kind of
structures casual structures which we
are which we have in our uh head and uh
maybe we investigate we invite more uh
specific better words better Concepts
better tools to describe those
structures but um I believe that for now
uh predictive
processing under the free energy
principle give us a good chance to
explain why our brains are not only the
matter but also the part the important
part of the living bodies and uh what is
the difference between the power the
brain as active control mechanism uh and
why this brain shouldn't be treated uh
as heat buff or thermal Reservoir and so
on and I think that and I think this is
the way this is the reason why beel uh
try to reformulate this the classical
image of the composition
because he um observes that some
mechanism cannot
be described or tra
as non- living
nonactive and
if they shouldn't be trated as act they
should be treated as active and living
then uh I think we have to to we have to
um try
to incorporate into our understanding
into our explanation the fact that the
information which the brains those
mechanism process is really really
important to understand why and how
they act how they are the part of
dissipative structures like our
organ thank you I'll ask a question next
from the live chat John Athos
wrote what are you defining as
information when you say the brain is
processing
information okay good questions
um I think um I think when I talk about
information I think about some kind of
semantic
information um of course if if we try
to use in practice this idea which I
Tred to develop uh the question about
information should be more specific more
more information should be more specify
but
um I find the argument which develop
Rosa I correctly
remember when she claims is that uh when
we talk about the information which is
processed by single neuron of course
this is the some kind of Sy information
there is no any semantic but with when
we want to try to understand how it is
possible that the brain as SP orgam the
cortex process information this is
always strictly related to the some kind
of semantic information and I
think we can think about this semantic
information um try to this but this is I
don't know for now how it is possible in
the realm of my argument but we think to
try about this what we traditionally
describe as semantic information in
terms of variational information because
I think that if brains minimize
prediction error if
brains approximate byan inference it
means that brain operates using
uses the information in semantic
semantic
sense um in my in my paper I wrote about
the uh the mutual information between
between the uh internal and sensory
States
um but I think I I see this is the as
lack of my view doesn't because I don't
prize what kind of information
precisely I mean but I think that if uh
we take this view as some kind of
um proposition of her ristic of building
the models um the empirical
investigations lead us to them to the uh
possibility of describe this information
more specific uh more uh specific
terms
awesome very interesting so a few lines
that I'd love to ask uh questions about
so in your paper and presentation you
Center the variational free energy as
kind of the analytical construct doing
the work in the mechanistic
account and I wondered what leads to one
analytical
construct doing that kind of work for
example why not Center
Surprise and see variational free energy
as a
computational puristic or just an
approximator
so what what would be the
relevance in in a mechanistic account
that
sensors the concept of surprise or the
concept of prediction error
versus the concept of variational free
energy which are related Concepts in
that an organism minimizing one does
minimize across
all but they are
different in terms of their formal basis
and what we could say about
them okay I think that
um I think that
if the answer on your question can be
can have two two parts the first one uh
is related to uh the view which I defend
as moderate realism I will and I will
claim
that
um notion we use the concept we use are
related are corresponds to the
structures which we try to develop and
describe using this Notions but in not
the sense that we literally map the
content of this Notions onto those those
Target phenomena
so probably V energy for now
looks a a good fit to those those
phenomena from my from my point of the
view but U it doesn't mean that we don't
can use the other Notions but you ask
why why we don't talk about surprise or
predictive errors I think that uh we
don't
explain
um in satisfaction
way uh this idea when we talk about the
surprise
maybe or prediction error because we
don't understand why uh White brain
approximate uh ban
inference if we don't introd the notion
of the vational free
energy or maybe it's equivalent to the
bot upper bound of surprise but if we
don't introduce this notion then we
don't don't find the compettion
uh formulation or compettion Foundation
to description of the brain working in
terms of minimalization of prediction
error
because I've got some problems with it
but maybe may may maybe uh try to
explain how I understand this if we take
the few um
um few level of description of David Mah
I think that talking about the minim
minimization of prediction error or
minimalization of uncertainity are
related uh to the uh compettion level
and I think that talking about
minimalization of R energy or
approximation by inference are related
to the algorithmic
level and the idea which I try to
develop is to using the connection
between those level to investigates
what's happened on the uh mechanistic uh
level the level of mar and I think that
the notion of prediction error or
Soo
um when we talk about this we omit
something important what describe and
explain friston his his paper concerning
the
energy yeah very interesting also
there's different ways to view this but
in the
vfe
centrism there's also the possibility of
relationality as a core principle
because if the mechanism surrounded
surprisal of the
system that would be closer to an
account where there was like a surprise
module or something that was
about what the systems what
representations were internal for the
system but with vfe we have something
that's explicitly
implementational relative to a
constructed
model so then
it it naturally um connects to
discussions about how modeling is done
as a
practice
be because
it is a constructed variable whereas
like temperature ostensibly it is
important
for a chemical
reaction or temperatures of core
graining I'm sure there's a lot of ways
to say it more formally but the the
kinetics do matter for the chemical
reaction and then we have tools that are
able
to measure temperature in different
settings cognitive
modeling seems to have a relational step
that's a lot more
[Music]
um
multifaceted because VF is only
calculated relative to the
modeler's
construct
so one person might make a model that
shows the vfe doing this and a different
model would show something different
and that seems to be a bit different
than like we have two
thermometers but we both agree that
temperature really does
matter yes yes I agree to agree but the
I think the information that the
dimension of information is more subtle
than uh the dimension of temperature of
mass and of course uh VF is related to
the modelers
and model which they develop but
um uh I tried to send something more of
course VF is related to the
modelers but there is something in the
uh Target
phenomena which motivate modelers to use
the
VF and of course if I
look on the piece of the
paper the paper does doesn't look
like for example process the information
and doesn't motivate me to to to think
about this paper as something what I can
model using uh the variational energy or
variational principle but when I talk
about on a living organism or the human
brain on on the something like that
there is something in the structure in
the phenomena which motivate me to build
a mod than using this um principle and
of course uh the truth of the method of
measurement the truth of the m method of
model building is arbitrary in the sense
that model uh the target
phenomena doesn't
directly give us an information which
method is better but uh it's not
arbitrary in the sense that I think that
we can in the same fruitful way use the
statistical mechan for example to
explain the brain and for example ban
modeling to explain the brain it's not
arbitrary in the sense that I can use
the the piece of paper to to eat
something as I can I can take a glass of
the water if I want to drink but I
cannot take a piece of paper if I
want if I wanted to drink but
but uh and this in in this sense when we
distinct the formal principle the
romatic principle we disting the model
which are built on the normative
principle and the target phenomena which
we want to explain using this model
based on the foral principle um then it
means
that the relation between the target
phenomena and the relation between the
model is not arbitrary in the sense that
we can use every kind of the model to
every kind of phenomena and I think that
um when we try to look into our
brains this kind of the structures in
some way motivate us to build the
compettion models and those compettion
models I think is in some sense
different than the compettion model for
example
of behavior of I don't know pones or
moving of my
hand
um and so um in general I would say that
uh truth
of and coming back to your
questions uh as I said the the dimension
of information the con informational
constraints are more uh more subtile
than the constraint like mass or
temperature because um probably we don't
have a as a same good uh method of
measurement of the information like we
have the good method of measurement of
temperature of the
mass and uh
probably maybe uh the free energy
principle or variational principles are
not the the
best possible way of describing and
explaining the brains but probably I
think there this is the most optimal for
this
moment uh when we take the the whole
knowledge our knowledge about the brains
it's the most the most optimal models
and methods to to trying to explain this
phenomena
but but as I said uh using of the
variational principles using of the
basian modeling doesn't
uh uh doesn't don't lead us to
the say something very specific
ontologically independent from these
models about the the nature of the
phenomena we
describe
thank you yeah that makes me think about
a sufficient account a mechanistic
account if you have a system that
entirely is described by hot and cold
flows through a
pipe you may have a sufficient and even
a total account with only
thermodynamics now maybe the hot and the
cold exactly signify like a signal so
then
there would need to be some kind of
information
processing model or
layering to understand and and then we
move into a space where
um looking at just the
information measures on the
syntax like the amount of data
transmitted in in bytes or something
over a digital
connection you've already already
highlighted the relevance of the
semantic information
flows which is um a topic that Chris
fields and others have started to look
into and then there's a further
uncoupling between the um material basis
of the information transfer and the
semantic information
flow I'll ask another question from the
live chat so upcycle Club wrote
are there any limitations or challenges
associated with incorporating
variational free energy models into
mechanisms yes good very very good
questions
um I think we can looking
for the
limitation related to
the uh questions which
scientist uh
gives uh uh it means that we can looking
for a limitation concerning the the the
the the
methods and of course the more important
limitation concerning the the border of
the of the systems and um it is hard to
give
a one good answer because in the field
of the in the field of the mechanical
philosophy there is a big discussion
about the border of the
mechanisms and if we take uh the
constraint based mechanism approach the
situation is looks more uh complicated
because um system Traditions uh of the
composing mechanism will claim that the
border of the mechanism are related to
the border of are related to the
components of the mechanism when I say
that the components of the
mechanism it's it means that something
what we de compose is not enough because
we have to also look into to the
elements which are not literally the
part of the mechanism but but which
makes the mechanism active it means that
the border of the mechanism is um
unclear and I think the main uh
limitation concerning my idea is
to is to say when we have to stop to
explain for
example when we take an example of the
pipe uh and the water moving in the
pipe um this is the part of the
mechanism but the the the the the the
material from which the pipe is built is
the Environmental constraints which is
not the part of the mechanism but which
is
important which is relevant for the
functioning of mechanism because the the
plastic pipe give
uh makes the better for example better
working of the mechanism than the wooden
pipe
and I think the main limitation is
related to the questions of
U which constraints for example when we
talk about the constraints as
environmental con uh environmental uh
factors which of the constraints
are uh how many constraints we need to
to say that okay this is enough we we
understand how this mechanism
isactive
um and I don't know for now uh where
this border is uh because opening the
mechanism on the constraints opening the
mechanism on the information coming or
processing by the for example narrow
mechanism make this questions about the
Border mechanics more specific or more
more
complicated um but I think this is
similar discussion or similar problem
like we find the the field of the FR
principle when we talk about the border
of the micro blankets or where we talk
about the the mark of the cognitive or
Mark of the living organism I think that
if we
integrate
mechanically the free energy principle
with the the the for example mechanical
predictive processing then uh then this
discussion about the border of
mechanism be a part of the discussion of
the border of Marco Blancas of the
border of informational systems
something like
that thank you that's a that's a huge
point it made me think about having a
physical object could be digital or
analog that's going to implement some
procedure program that is going to be
bound apparently by the halting problem
like the inability to know for some
kinds of systems how the pro the program
is going to turn out um by the
incompleteness type pattern so there's
certain informational constraints that
kind of come out of nowhere seemingly to
constrain the um
action or to to provide some
some thing that limits the action or the
knowability of the action so then you um
highlighted that it
it is actually this stopping time
question or the halting question as a
question of scientific strategy in
building
accounts knowing how much to include and
and that's very related to like
identifying or selecting a system of
interest because you could say well the
pipe comes from here and so we're going
to go back up the supply chain and
pretty soon if you include the flow of
air or the movement of digital
information or something like that in
the
system that can unfold to
include untenable
models so then there's a course
graining and all already um people make
informational core screenings like with
causal
influence diagram
like just the the the the relevance of
one variable on
another and so it's just very
interesting that by having the material
Thermo
mechanism and a
legitimated role or status for
informational
mechanisms which are the natural kind of
explanation for perhaps algorithms or
information
processing
that still there's the the boundedness
of what is being accounted
for
but a clearer way to know how far out
informationally just like you could go
out physically in the thermal
account with layers of rooms outside of
the heat bath
also you could go out informationally
more into the past for example or you
can just say we're just drawing a line
around
this so maybe by yeah sorry sorry no I
think I think that the the the for maybe
the best way is to um question about on
the of the borders of the mechanism
borders of the system relative device to
the our scientific
interesting because when we talk for
example when we talk about the pipe or
we talk about the digital system um they
are some kind of artifacts and they are
related to the architecture who made
them when we talk about the brain it is
hard to think about the brain in the
same or analogous sense and we talk
about the pipe or the glass or the paper
because there are artifacts you can say
about natural artifacts and I think
that our uh thinking about the borders
of the system we want to describe maybe
primary should be related to the our our
questions concerning the
borders and pro maybe it the story was
that that mechanists
um in this system tradition the
traditional VI mechanism um will say
something like that
we think about the brains
as mechanism like the other
one we can we can develop the the
structure of the the of the Social Web
the structure of the uh of the brain the
structure of the the bones and so on and
so
on uh and this this way of thinking
about the brain as the kind of the
mechanics like the other one in some
sense uh
direct the investigation into brains and
this is why for example the composition
as the whole strategy new mechanical
philosophy many
authors think about this as as relevant
and uh we don't need anything
else but when Beal for example claims
that okay but there is a mistake because
our
brains are based on the web of active
mechanism and those active mechanism is
most more specific because
uh what makes them active is not
only it's not is not only what makes
them and mechanism in traditional normal
sense and when we talk when we look into
the paper of
Beal he doesn't develop the the idea of
talking about the whole brain they
developed the the investigation into the
small pieces of how some kinds of cells
transform uh molecules and so on and so
on
but they they still uh claims that if
we uh show the bound
into too fast then uh then we don't
explain correctly how the given
mechanism the given cells uh do actively
what does what actively what it does and
um I don't know if if
um probably if I want to the defend the
idea of moderate realism about ban
modeling I would like to say something
like that
that that there are some kind of borders
in the
world um we try looking for those
borders um maybe this this the systems
and the difference between different
systems uh motivate us to try and
describe these borders but um there is
no possibility to say that the factor
here there is a borders but always when
we talk about the borders this is
talking about the borders is related to
our our uh measurement tools and uh the
method so I think
that the small move in mechanical
philosophy which I describe as the
constraint based mean approach um we can
interpretate as
um as uh example of uh the situation
when the phenomena motivate us to change
our scientific
practice because
uh back 20 or 30 30 years developed the
the new mechanical philosophy but in
last five or six years he claims that
okay but this old
view was not perfect we have to change
something and I think this is this is
the argument for the moderate
interpretation of the scientific
practice phenomena in some sense because
we developed a good method to
investigate into phenomena PHA in some
sense motivate us to change to to to to
to uh develop the the the new
methods and change our our scientific uh
horis and so on
so
wow that's awesome one other thing it
made me think about was the
differences the the relevance or the
difference between the thermodynamic and
the informational
accounts become very clear when studying
decentralized
systems that are spatially
disaggregated because when there's
something that's physically
enclosed and and it has like a unitary
physical component and a unitary
informational component like a desktop
computer or a single
tissue then there is an
undeniable
um
overlap between those
two
systems which kind of host and relate to
each
other but then when there's a system
that um has other things amidst
it that than just thinking here about
Nest mates in the ant
colony well then spatial enclosure and
just inclusion of all the material
components seems to clearly capture too
much and
so that seems to suggest a more
informational
role which takes on
many rich areas from semiotics and all
these other semantic questions not just
again a reduction of the
informational to the syntactic
informational
like how
much um energy or material was
transferred because again that will
just
conflate that'll make Mech it's it's
it's um it's a approach that won't lead
to the best research agenda on
mechanistic
accounts
interesting h
so I think that the the the the the
question about semantic information uh
is really important here but if we take
uh basian ideas about the the brain
which infer the information coming from
uh the environment this is
thisinformation is something more than
the syntactic
relation
um but um I think I think what is
important uh here is what what what what
PR's really important claims that I
think that uh information change
everything in that sense
that when we try to literally think
about um bi approximation and so on then
it means that everything we want to
describe and explain as scientist is
stly related to the information we
receive you of course this is very very
simple
but
uh every every object uh we observe
every object we want to
describe uh is always related to the
information we have about this object
and it means that there is
no something like we got a naked fact
naked State of Affairs uh
maybe ontologically there are but from
the point of the view of the entities
like us every time when we receive when
some information every time when we
observe something and we try to develop
a model of some kind of phenomena it's
it's always um related to the some kind
of information what we have about this
phenomena and
uh I try to say something
very met
metaphysical
uh
um I think that the varal
uh uh point of the view as we can say
something like that the bian point of
the view um show us that there is no
distinct border between the the the the
object
we try to
map uh between the the language we try
to use to map this object
because I think there is
something that Max rad has right when we
they claim that we still we try to
describe the objects who behave like the
that we try to describe the territory
which behave like a map which describe
this territory
and of course this is not only the
metaphor I think
that uh everything what scientist try to
do is to reconfigure is to
identify the
structures uh which um are extended now
to the structure uh of thinking
structure of information in which we use
um I don't know
I think that that that
bayian view about human brains about the
world uh lead us to the one uh very
important questions about
um about the informational natur nature
of the
world I don't know
um I spec right now okay but when we
when we
think when we take seriously this uh
kind of thinking about a science about
about the entities the most basic the
most
fundamental uh future of the world it's
not a mass it's not a temperature it's
not an energy but an
information and I think the information
is something what change a difference
and uh literally it means that if you
want to develop a science we cannot
ignore this very
basic fundamental futures of the world
why because the information of course I
don't want to say it's something like
pism P informational something like that
but I will say that information is
always for he for
someone and
um
and and I would like to say
that from some some when when I reading
the papers of freom and so on I I still
think about what why we should or why we
shouldn't uh ignore the information in
our investigation and I think
that ban uh
modeling give us a good tool maybe it's
a ple for uh the place of information in
the in the in the science
because but not only literally talking
about information okay we not it's
obvious that brain process information
but information is antiy which making
possible many many of the phenomena and
I think that our
brains in short we say our brains are
the entities which
are which are possible because there are
information which makes this mechanism
this kind of mechanism but not the
other sorry I this I think this is
really speculative uh metaphysical uh
but it's hard
to catch this
idea yeah there's there's a lot there um
certainly the unity of the scientific
and the broader informational Endeavor
is very
interesting and so thinking about that
explicitly in terms of epistemic
foraging seeking out which measurements
or observations to
acrew and that being kind of on a
Continuum of agency of experimental
selection and there's other like a fixed
camera does not have control
over the
sensory observations it's making it
could have internal cognitive control
but but having a unified way to talk
about what it is that science or just
different ways of knowing even outside
of what we might call Professional
science today that those
different
manifestations are are part of a
ecosystem of Shar intelligence part of a
shared fabric with other information
processing
as chemical elements are in circulation
in a chemical
[Music]
ecosystem what is the status of the
semantic
informational
Connections in semantic
ecosystems and people could have
viewpoints like well there are no
semantic ecosystems there's just
syntactic ones and you know there's no
syntactic ones there's just material
ones I mean people can always go that
reductionist
path but to the point where any given
person says okay I've kind of bottomed
out on reductionism here or I'm looking
for another perspective there is going
to be the question of what the semantic
account
is and what its status is and does it
articulate with the thermodynamic
account do they have a a zone of
indistinguishability
do they have um a broadly
overlapping
region maybe it could be one way in one
system and a different way in a
different system
system but these will constitute like
some of the fundamental philosophy
questions that that you identified in
terms of real mechanistic accounts for
intelligent systems
and using active inference to develop
any kind of
account I think we cannot ignore the
semantic uh and
maybe the one of the most important
things that fristom says is that
semantic is important in that sense
that it is not only the the
medium uh which we use for example when
we if I correctly understand the the the
origins of the the the fian free energy
principle it comes from the method of
measurement of the in
activity
and someone can say okay this is only
the method and there is no any
implication uh of course but I think
that the Fone
will say something more it says
that there are phenomena which in which
semantics play and not only the uh of
course there is phenomena in which
semantics play an important role
but we cannot ignore the semantic
Dimension
um in our practice of uh science
building or model building uh it means
that semantic is not something like the
piece of the paper I can use the piece
of the paper when I have wrote uh a
paper or I can uh use a word or offic
and something like that and this not
important what a material use I think
that many authors or maybe papers think
about the semantic as some kind of the
medium like the kind of the paper I use
I think that
the re energy active inference framework
show us
that the information or semantic is
something uh what makes
possible for example to to to to to do
this to do a science or make or maybe
the information semantic is some is
something what makes possible for as a
human human being
and maybe like a
thermodynamic free energy if we don't uh
transform the the mules from the
environment we don't live but the
question is why uh
science talk many things about the
thermodynamic
processes and talk enough not enough uh
about the informational processes I
think that the biam
modeling uh FR approach lead us to the
conclusion that there are systems for
which the transfer informations is uh a
same important like to transform process
the thermodynamic energy in the argument
which I tried to develop from the ne
computation show us
that all always there is a tradeoff
there is a comprom there is a relation
between information processing and
thermodynamic work Coast if there is
some kind of tradeoff
why we don't uh take an usage but Pro
probably it as I said uh information is
something what is hard to uh be measured
like temperature like mass and and so on
and so on and I believe that um veral
principles uh give us a chance to try to
develop this of course remembering about
this that those principles are only the
those principles lead us to the tools
which are only the the more or better
more or minor the approximation of the
the the real real
phenomena
um okay
well wow do you have any closing
thoughts or where is your research in
this area going to
go uh I think that
uh I've got a I've wrote a grand
proposal about this idea and a few days
ago I I received a reject in
Polish
Center um and the one of them I think
this the the the the one the reason why
they reject my proposal is that I I
don't
propose uh um using appli this idea into
the the real modeling framework so the
next steps I and I think I agree because
this is very speculative uh I propos
some kind of horis sixs and I believe
that this hortic can be applied in a
real model building strategy and uh the
next step about now I'm
thinking is that to to Mid person or to
to make a competence concerning that and
find the finding the way to how to taste
this idea in in practice
um and still um there is two options um
the first one is that okay this is the
the the speculative idea and we don't
need think about the the the
mechanism in terms of information
constraints and so on and so on and the
second is that okay this is a correct
idea but but maybe variational principle
bi modeling is useless here
because everything what you need is
coming from the thermodynamic of
information or the classical theory of
information like and so on so I think
there are many open doors
I hope I
will take a way to find some of
them thank you well it was a great
presentation and discussion you're
welcome back anytime to share what that
next step looks like I really appreciate
this I think it
certainly is a great benefit to the
literature to connect
the kinds of things that people want to
say and
do
to now how we are saying and doing
it thank you thank you Daniel thank you
very much thanks for
questions that was a very nice
experience thank you excellent all right
till next time good night bye
bye